Guide to the Roland Herbert Bainton Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Roland Herbert Bainton Papers
1886-1988
RG 75
Yale University Divinity School Library
35
86 boxes
Extensive correspondence, writings, notes, and illustrations document Bainton's roles as lecturer, researcher, artist, world traveler, friend to the oppressed, ardent pacifist, teacher, and mentor. Bainton was born in England and emigrated first to Canada in 1898 and then to the United States in 1902. He taught church history at Yale Divinity School from 1920 to 1962, serving as Titus Street Professor of Ecclesiastical History from 1936. Bainton wrote prolifically and was an authority on Luther and the Reformation, Christian attitudes toward war, Congregational history, and the history of the Yale Divinity School.
Bainton, Roland H. (Roland Herbert), 1894-1984
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Bainton family, 1984, 2014.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
For more detailed biographical information see the chronology in A Bainton Bibliography by Cynthia Wales Lund, Box 11.
Chronology 1894 March 30 Born in Ilkeston, Derbyshire, England, son of Jame Herbert Bainton, Congregational pastoral, and Charlotte Blackham Bainton 1898 Moved to Vancouver, British Columbia 1902 Moved to Colfax, Washington 1914 Graduated from Whitman College, B.A. degree in Classics. 1917 Graduated from Yale Divinity School with B.D. degree 1918-1919 Declared pacifism serving without military rank in a unit of the American Friends Service Committee under the American Red Cross in France. 1920 Appointed instructor in Church History and New Testament at Yale Divinity School 1921 Received Ph.D.degree in Semitics and Hellenistic Greek from Yale University 1921 Jun 8 Married Ruth Mae Woodruff 1923 Promoted to Assistant Professor at Yale Divinity School. Dissertation published: Basilidian Chronology and New Testament Interpretation 1926 Awarded Guggenheim Fellowship. Studied in Swiss archives researching proponents of religious liberty during the Reformation 1927 Ordained as Congregational minister 1932 Promoted to Associate Professor 1935-1962 Titus Street Professor of Ecclesiastical History at Yale Divinity School 1962 Professor Emeritus 1984 Died Memberships and positions:
Chronology
1894 March 30 Born in Ilkeston, Derbyshire, England, son of Jame Herbert Bainton, Congregational pastoral, and Charlotte Blackham Bainton
1898 Moved to Vancouver, British Columbia
1902 Moved to Colfax, Washington
1914 Graduated from Whitman College, B.A. degree in Classics.
1917 Graduated from Yale Divinity School with B.D. degree
1918-1919 Declared pacifism serving without military rank in a unit of the American Friends Service Committee under the American Red Cross in France.
1920 Appointed instructor in Church History and New Testament at Yale Divinity School
1921 Received Ph.D.degree in Semitics and Hellenistic Greek from Yale University
1921 Jun 8 Married Ruth Mae Woodruff
1923 Promoted to Assistant Professor at Yale Divinity School. Dissertation published: Basilidian Chronology and New Testament Interpretation
1926 Awarded Guggenheim Fellowship. Studied in Swiss archives researching proponents of religious liberty during the Reformation
1927 Ordained as Congregational minister
1932 Promoted to Associate Professor
1935-1962 Titus Street Professor of Ecclesiastical History at Yale Divinity School
1962 Professor Emeritus
1984 Died
Scope and Contents
These records document many facets of Bainton's long and full life. Though most renowned as a leader in the field of Reformation church history, Bainton's interests and expertise ranged over a broad spectrum - from Congregationalism and his Non-conformist heritage to issues of war and peace, from concerns of the pastoral ministry to chronicles of Yale history. Extensive correspondence, writings, notes, and illustrations in the Bainton Papers document his roles as scintillating lecturer, persistent researcher, perceptive artist, world traveler, friend to the oppressed, ardent pacifist, teacher and mentor to many.
Series I, FAMILY CORRESPONDENCE, includes two types of material: 1) correspondence of Bainton and his immediate and extended family, and 2) correspondence from the previous generation, including letters of Bainton's parents to both family and acquaintances. Correspondence of Bainton with family members is relatively scarce, but the letters available do reveal Bainton's personal warmth and dynamism. According to Bainton's autobiography, he corresponded frequently with his sister Hilda throughout his college and seminary years; neither these letters nor any consistent run of correspondence with his parents appear in this collection. Letters exchanged by Bainton and his son Cedric constitute the most substantive run of correspondence in the Series. Some family circular letters are interfiled in this section.
Series II, GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE, includes letters written throughout the span of Bainton's more than sixty years of professional scholarly activity. Letters to and from friends, colleagues, students, publishers, organizations, admirers and critics document in a thorough way Bainton's collegial and personal relationships. Prominent correspondents are listed individually and include Heinrich Bornkamm, George L. Burr, Robert Calhoun, Paul Oskar Kristeller, H. Richard Niebuhr, Heiko Oberman, Wilhelm Pauck and Gerhard Ritter. Certain famous correspondents, such as Erwin Panofsky, George McGovern and Johann Huizenga, have not been listed as prominent correspondents because their letters are neither regular nor substantive. Bainton's commitment to scholarship did not preclude his devotion to the church and to humanity. His correspondence amply reveals his lifelong integration of scholarship, friendship and social concern. A poignant illustration of this is found in letters exchanged with Italian historian Delio Cantimori. Their correspondence began solely for scholarly purposes but, in need of clothes after the devastation of World War II in Italy, Cantimori sent Bainton a tracing of his feet for shoes. Bainton sent him a pair of his own. Correspondence with Paul Oskar Kristeller and Elisabeth Feist Hirsch provides notable documentation of Bainton's relationship with European scholars who sought refuge from Nazi Germany. Some additional correspondence related to Bainton's writings and biographical material can be found in Series III and VIII respectively.
Series III, WRITINGS / TALKS, is organized according to the categories established in the extensive bibliography of Bainton's works compiled by Cynthia W. Lund in 1979. The original manuscript of this bibliography is located at the beginning of the Series; it is followed by a photocopy annotated with additional published works which came to light in processing the Bainton Papers. Series III also expands upon the Lund bibliography by including unpublished writings, drafts, addresses, sermons, prayers, etc. There is relatively little material related to Bainton's major monographs in this Series. There is material related to Bainton's autobiography, which was edited and published posthumously. The Series includes complete manuscripts or offprints of some works, drafts and notes specifically relating to manuscripts, numerous unpublished works, and some correspondence related to the production and reception of published works. Additional notes and source materials for Bainton's writings can be found under the title of the work in Series V, NOTES/SOURCE MATERIALS.
The COURSE-RELATED MATERIAL of Series IV consists primarily of lecture notes, bibliographical materials arranged by Bainton and other material related to Bainton's courses at the Yale Divinity School. Folder labels in the sections organized by topic and by course title duplicate those in Bainton's filing system. Within a given folder there may be a mixture of lectures, notes, and collected material related to a particular topic or course. Nearly all the typescript lecture notes are from the 1920s and 1930s; Bainton rarely used notes in lecturing during his later years of teaching. The majority of handwritten notes in this Series are in the cryptic shorthand which Bainton learned as a youth. A published manual describing this shorthand system is available in Series V.
Series V, NOTES/SOURCE MATERIALS, documents Bainton's research interests over a period of more than sixty years. Handwritten notes, collected photostats and copies, and other materials are arranged topically. As in the case of Series IV, the folder labels in this Series have been taken directly from Bainton's own designations and are not ideally descriptive in all cases. The material in a particular folder may be broader or more narrow in scope than the folder label would suggest. Materials listed under the title of a published work by Bainton may be more or less directly related to that work.
Series IV contains both illustrations collected by Bainton and his own artwork. Bainton's celebrated caricatures and sketches of colleagues, friends, and scenes demonstrate his perceptive eye, artistic talent, and lifelong habit of spontaneously setting pen to paper. The collected illustrations in this Series relate primarily to the history of Christianity. Prints, photocopies, negatives, clippings are arranged in two sequences, by the title of the monograph for which they were collected, or by topic. Once again, the folder labels in the topical sequence are in most cases those devised by Bainton. A section of 35mm slides completes the Series.
The COLLECTED MATERIAL of Series VII is a sampling of materials sent to or acquired by Bainton over many years. The Series is divided into three categories: 1) Bibliographies by others, 2) Writings by others, and 3) Material on contemporary social and political issues. The writings by others retained in this Series are those which may not be easily accessible in published format. The materials in the third category date primarily from the late 1960s through the early 1980s and reflect Bainton's intense interest in peace and social/political affairs.
Series VIII, PERSONAL ITEMS AND MEMORABILIA, begins with biographical statements and articles about Bainton which provide concise documentation of his life and work. Additional biographical insights are provided by a sequence of bulletins, clippings, announcements, etc. which document Bainton's activities over the years. Tributes and reminiscences by former colleagues and students provide yet another window of insight on Bainton's life. The material following this section of biographical documentation is divided into three categories: memorabilia, family history, and photographs. Bainton's famous Christmas cards are included in the memorabilia section. The family history section includes extensive material related to Bainton's father and material related to the Brotherhood Movement founded in England by Bainton's maternal grandfather, John Blackham. The photographs include portraits of Bainton throughout his life, family photos, and numerous photographs of the Bainton and Blackham families from the late 19th century.
Arrangement
I. Family Correspondence
II. General Correspondence
III. Writings / Talks
IV. Course-related Materials
V. Notes/ Source Materials
VI. Illustrations/ Artwork
VII. Collected Material
VIII. Personal Items and Memorabilia
Congregationalism; Pacifism -- Religious aspects -- Christianity; Reformation; Educators; Bainton, Roland H. (Roland Herbert), 1894-1984; Bornkamm, Heinrich, 1901-1977; Burr, George Lincoln, 1857-1938; Cantimori, Delio; Hirsch, Elisabeth Feist; Kristeller, Paul Oskar, 1905-1999; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Divinity School
- Family Correspondence, Series I
  - Roland H. Bainton
    - RHB to/from his parents, 1916,1919,1941,1959 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - RHB to/from wife, Ruth, 1920,1934,1937 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - RHB to/from his children Herbert, Olive, Ruth, Joyce (incl. some memorabilia of children), 1942-1980, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - RHB to/from son Cedric, 1943-1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - RHB to/from son Cedric, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - RHB to/from son Cedric, 1951-1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - RHB to/from his grandchildren, 1972-1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - RHB to/from his sister and her family, 1935-1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - RHB from Harold and Olive Blackham, 1970-1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - RHB from various other relatives, 1931-1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Ruth Woodruff Bainton
    - RWB to immediate family, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - RWB to parents of RWB and RHB, 1937,1956 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - RWB to unidentified correspondents, 1937-1957,n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Emily Blackham Bainton (stepmother of RHB)
    - EBB to James Herbert Bainton, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - EBB from grandchildren and great-grandchildren, 1953-1960 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - EBB from extended family, 1913-1959 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - EBB from friends, 1941-1960 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - J. Herbert and Emily Blackham Bainton
    - JHB and EBB from George and Sallie Purcell, 1913-1934 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - JHB and EBB from George and Sallie Purcell, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - (excerpts from George Purcell diary), 1936 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - (excerpts from George Purcell diary), 1937-1942 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - JHB and EBB from George, Sallie, Mary Purcell, 1949-1959 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - J. Herbert Bainton (father of RHB)
    - To JHB from parents, 1886-1897 (Box 2, Folder 23-28)
    - To JHB from father, 1898 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - To JHB from sister, 1888-1917 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - To JHB from others, 1890-1937,n.d. (Box 2, Folder 31,32)
    - Family of JHB to Lottie Blackham Bainton, 1892,1893,n.d. (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Letters collected by JHB (incl. from William Jennings Bryan and Clara Barton) (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Edgar Blackham (uncle of RHB)
    - Misc. correspondence and writings (Box 2, Folder 35)
- General Correspondence, Series II
  Scope and Contents
  The majority of the correspondence is arranged alphabetically by the last name of the sender or recipient other than Bainton. A sequence of folders for each letter of the alphabet (e.g. Ab-Al, Am-Au) is followed by individual folders for prominent correspondents with names beginning with that letter (e.g. Alcalá, Angel). The correspondence of prominent correspondents is arranged chronologically. Following the alphabetical sequence, three types of letters are grouped separately: letters requesting recommendations from Bainton; letters of recommendation by Bainton, and requests for books, photographs, other related material. An addendum of correspondence includes a folder of World War II era correspondence with and regarding professor that Bainton help to resettle in the U.S, including Paul Oskar Kristeller and others.
  - Ab - Al (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Am - Au (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Alcalá, Angel, 1971-1981 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Allen, Thelma Diener, 1976-1985 (Box 84, Folder 11)
  - Althaus, Paul, 1948,1951 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Bac - Bay (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Bea - Ben (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Ber - Bi (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Bl - Bo (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Br - By (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Bainton to "Dear Friend" - circular letter soliciting funds for the International Committee for Securing Employment to Refugee Professional Workers, 1947 (Box 84, Folder 5)
  - Barczyk, Cecylia, 1978-1981 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Begin, Menachim, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Bornkamm, Heinrich, 1950-1967 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Brooks, Peter, 1971-1979 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Bultmann, Rudolph, 1950,1957 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Burr, George L. (incl. collected letters), 1926-1937,n.d. (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Ca (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Ce - Ch (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Cl - Coo (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Cop - Cor (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Cou - Cy (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Calhoun, Robert, 1920-1922, 1978,1979 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Campenhausen, Hans, 1949-1975 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Cantimori, Delio, 1932-1966,n.d. (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Cassirer, Ernst, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Da - Det (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Dev - Di (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Do - Du (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Danforth, John (incl. re. citizenship of Douglas Clyde Macintosh), 1977,1981 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - DeKuczynski, Heinz, 1942-1953 (Box 85, Folder 6)
  - Demura, Akira, 1963-1981 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Dickens, A.G., 1966-1973 (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - Dinkler, Erich and Erika, 1948, 1965-1980 (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - Dorries, Hermann, 1951,1961-1970,n.d. (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - Ea - Eg (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - Ei - Er (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - Es - Ey (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - Ebeling, Gerhard, 1950-1953 (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - Erikson, Erik, 1971,1977 (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - Fa - Fl (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - Fo - Fred (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - Free - Fu (Box 4, Folder 75)
  - Fulton, John, 1931-1954 (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - Ga - Ge (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - Gi - Gl (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - Go - Gra (Box 5, Folder 79)
  - Gre - Gri (Box 5, Folder 80)
  - Gru - Gu (Box 5, Folder 81)
  - Gilson, Etienne, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 82)
  - Gonzalez, Justo, 1962-1969 (Box 5, Folder 83)
  - Grosser, M., 1963 (Box 84, Folder 5)
  - Hac - Harr (Box 5, Folder 84)
  - Hart - Hel (Box 5, Folder 85)
  - Hen - Hj (Box 5, Folder 86)
  - Ho (Box 5, Folder 87)
  - Hu - Hy (Box 5, Folder 88)
  - Hillerbrand, Hans, 1961,1967-1969,n.d. (Box 5, Folder 89)
  - Hirsch, Elisabeth Feist (incl. essay re. her friendship with Bainton), 1933-1939,1958-1981 (Box 5, Folder 90)
  - I (Box 5, Folder 90a)
  - Ja - Joh (Box 5, Folder 91)
  - Jon - Ju (Box 5, Folder 92)
  - Ka (Box 5, Folder 93)
  - Ke - Ki (Box 5, Folder 94)
  - Kl - Kr (Box 6, Folder 95)
  - Ku (Box 6, Folder 96)
  - Kingdon, Robert, 1951-1969,1980 (Box 6, Folder 97)
  - Köhler, Werner, 1926-1940,n.d. (Box 6, Folder 98)
  - Kot, Stanislaw, 1949-1958 (Box 6, Folder 99)
  - Kristeller, Paul Oskar, 1938-1940 (Box 6, Folder 100)
  - Kristeller, Paul Oskar, 1941-1953 (Box 6, Folder 101)
  - Kristeller, Paul Oskar, 1954-1963 (Box 6, Folder 102)
  - Kristeller, Paul Oskar, 1964-1975 (Box 6, Folder 103)
  - Kristeller, Paul Oskar, 1976-1983 (Box 6, Folder 104)
  - La (Box 6, Folder 105)
  - Le - Lin (Box 6, Folder 106)
  - Lis - Lo (Box 6, Folder 107)
  - Lu - Ly (Box 6, Folder 108)
  - Langerbeck, Elisabeth, 1969-1981 (Box 6, Folder 109)
  - Lefever, Ernest W., 1981 (Box 6, Folder 110)
  - Loewenich, Walthar von, 1948-1980 (Box 6, Folder 111)
  - Maa - Mac (incl. Mc) (Box 7, Folder 112)
  - Mad - Mar (Box 7, Folder 113)
  - Mas - Men (Box 7, Folder 114)
  - Mer - Mi (Box 7, Folder 115)
  - Mo (Box 7, Folder 116)
  - Mu - My (Box 7, Folder 117)
  - McNeill, John T., 1932,1937,1944 (Box 7, Folder 118)
  - Marquez, Antonio, 1970-1976 (Box 7, Folder 119)
  - Miller, Perry, 1948,1951,1954 (Box 7, Folder 120)
  - Mott, John R., 1930,1944,1953 (Box 7, Folder 121)
  - Nac - Nak (Box 7, Folder 122)
  - Nat (Box 7, Folder 123)
  - Ned - Nel (Box 7, Folder 124)
  - Neu - Nic (Box 7, Folder 125)
  - Nie - Nu (Box 7, Folder 126)
  - Nelson, J. Robert, 1952-1983 (Box 84, Folder 9)
  - Niebuhr, H. Richard, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 127)
  - Nieto, José, 1964-1981,n.d. (Box 7, Folder 128)
  - Nuttall, Geoffrey, 1949-1966 (Box 7, Folder 129)
  - Oa - Ol (Box 7, Folder 130)
  - Om - Ow (Box 7, Folder 131)
  - Oberman, Heiko, 1961-1980 (Box 7, Folder 132)
  - O'Malley, Charles, 1934-1956 (Box 7, Folder 133)
  - Pa (Box 8, Folder 134)
  - Pe - Pl (Box 8, Folder 135)
  - Po - Py (Box 8, Folder 136)
  - Pauck, Wilhelm and Marion, 1951-1979,n.d. (Box 8, Folder 137)
  - Phillips, Margaret, 1969-1980 (Box 8, Folder 138)
  - Promoting Enduring Peace, Inc., 1967-1981 (Box 8, Folder 139)
  - Publishers: A - C (Box 8, Folder 140)
  - Publishers: D - Ha (Box 8, Folder 141)
  - Publishers: Ho - P (Box 8, Folder 142)
  - Publishers: S - W (Box 8, Folder 143)
  - Q (Box 8, Folder 144)
  - Ra - Rei (Box 8, Folder 145)
  - Rel - Ri (Box 8, Folder 146)
  - Rob - Rol (Box 8, Folder 147)
  - Ros - Ru (Box 8, Folder 148)
  - Rabil, Albert, Jr., 1966-1979 (Box 9, Folder 149)
  - Roelker, Nancy, 1968-1971 (Box 9, Folder 150)
  - Ritter, Gerhard, 1938-1961 (Box 9, Folder 151)
  - Rotondò, Antonio, 1967-1974 (Box 9, Folder 152)
  - Rupp, Gordon P.; Rupp, E.G., 1947-1965 (Box 9, Folder 153)
  - Sa (Box 9, Folder 154)
  - Sch (Box 9, Folder 155)
  - Se - Sk (Box 9, Folder 156)
  - Sm - Sp (Box 9, Folder 157)
  - St - Sw (Box 9, Folder 158)
  - Sanchez Barbudo, Angela, 1953-1978 (Box 9, Folder 159)
  - Schrey, Heinz and Marianne, 1947 (Box 85, Folder 4)
  - Smith, Preserved, 1929-1939 (Box 9, Folder 160)
  - Strong, Tracy, 1940 (Box 84, Folder 5)
  - Ta - Thom (Box 9, Folder 161)
  - Thor - Tu (Box 9, Folder 162)
  - Thompson, Craig, 1946-1948, 1965-1979 (Box 9, Folder 163)
  - Thomson, S. Harrison, 1927-1943 (Box 9, Folder 164)
  - U (Box 9, Folder 165)
  - Va - Ve (Box 9, Folder 166)
  - Vi - Vo (Box 9, Folder 167)
  - Wa (Box 10, Folder 168)
  - We - Wic (Box 10, Folder 169)
  - Wil - Wu (Box 10, Folder 170)
  - Wilbur, Earl (Box 10, Folder 171)
  - Y (Box 10, Folder 172)
  - Z (Box 10, Folder 173)
  - Letter to YDS alumni, written at age 89 (Box 10, Folder 174)
  - First names only: A - M (Box 10, Folder 175)
  - First names only: N - Z (Box 10, Folder 176)
  - Unidentified (Box 10, Folder 177)
  - Letters requesting recommendations from Bainton (Box 10, Folder 178)
  - Letters of recommendation by Bainton (Box 10, Folder 179)
  - Requests for books, photographs, other related material: A - F (Box 10, Folder 180)
  - Requests for books, photographs, other related material: G - N (Box 10, Folder 181)
  - Requests for books, photographs, other related material: O - Z (Box 10, Folder 182)
  - Miscellaneous letters with colleagues and regarding lectures, trips, writings, including from Alexander Biro, Ernst Benz, Heinrich Bornkamm, Wilhelm Pauck, Bernadotte Schmitt, Paul Kristeller, 1946-1967 (Box 85, Folder 2)
  - Letters to/from publishers, 1961-1974 (Box 85, Folder 3)
  - WWII era letters from and about European professors, including Paul Oskar Kristeller, Edward Lowinsky, Ernst Breisacher, Karl Heussi, Peter Brunner, Will-Erich Peuckert, Gerhard Ebeling, Lamberto Borghi - regarding resettlement in U.S. (see also individual folders for Schrey, DeKuczynski, Kristeller, Ebeling), 1939-1949 (Box 85, Folder 5)
  - Letters re. trips to South America, Asia, Kenya, Lebanon, 1960-1971 (Box 85, Folder 7)
  - Letters re. Poland / Yale Committee on Cultural Relations with Poland, 1974-1976 (Box 85, Folder 8)
- Writings / Talks, Series III
  This Series is divided according to the following categories and subcategories:
  Studies in church history
  re. teaching and writing
  re. issues of war and peace
  re. concerns of the pastoral ministry
  re. popular faith and preaching
  re. the Church and society
  re. Quakers
  re. Yale
  Miscellaneous
  - Bibliographies of Bainton's works
    - "Bibliography of Works By and About Roland H. Bainton" by Cynthia W. Lund- original, 1979 (Box 11, Folder 183)
    - "Bibliography of Works By and About Roland H. Bainton" by Cynthia W. Lund - photocopy, with addenda (Box 11, Folder 184)
    - "Bibliography of Works By and About Roland H. Bainton" by Cynthia W. Lund - notes (Box 11, Folder 185)
    - Other bibliographies (Box 11, Folder 186)
  - Monographs
    - Debtors to God, 1930 (Box 11, Folder 187)
    - Bibliography of the Continental Reformation, 1935 (Box 11, Folder 188)
    - Concerning Heretics - letters, partial drafts, 1935 (Box 11, Folder 189)
    - David Joris - draft, 1937 (Box 11, Folder 190)
    - David Joris - draft (Box 12, Folder 191)
    - David Joris - draft (Box 12, Folder 192)
    - David Joris - letters (Box 12, Folder 193)
    - Bernardino Ochino - draft, 1940 (Box 12, Folder 194)
    - Bernardino Ochino - draft (Box 12, Folder 195)